I'm Jenn Schilling, and today I'm going to talk
about how to set the focus order on a Tableau
dashboard. When I made the COVID-19 dashboard
for the University of Arizona, where I work as
a senior data analyst, the focus order became an
issue immediately after the dashboard went live.
I'm going to share why focus order
matters, how it can be set within Tableau,
and the implications to data visualization as a
whole. Before we get started, let's define focus
order. Focus order is the order in which a user
accesses elements of a web page or a dashboard.
And normally we would want a user or viewer of our
dashboards to access them in a sequential order
top to bottom, left to right. In Tableau,
though, when we add elements to a dashboard
the focus order is automatically set for us, and
it's set by the order in which elements are added.
So, as we're building the dashboard each time we
add a new sheet or a new element to the dashboard
that element gets an ID and that ID determines
the focus order. Normally as we're building
and designing dashboards we're not necessarily
thinking about the top to bottom, left to right
sequence or final order of the layout of the
dashboard, so this becomes an issue when those
IDs are automatically set for us. And i'm going
to show you an example here where the red arrow
is going to show the focus order and reading
through this screenshot of part of the dashboard.
So it starts with the title but then it goes down
to the past 10 days and then it goes back up to
the date when data was last pulled, it goes down
to the graph and back up to the most recent day.
So as you saw that's not the logical top to
bottom, left to right order, but we can fix this.
Underneath a Tableau workbook is an XML file, and
so if the workbook is saved as a .tbw you can open
that file in a text editor and edit the XML. Each
element on a dashboard is contained within a zone
element in the XML, and each of these zone elements
has an ID attribute. By setting the ID attributes,
we set the focus order. So what we can do is go
back through our dashboard, and in each element
we can set the focus order to be a logical number
or order from that top to bottom, left to right
that we want the user to access our dashboard
and read our dashboard. Some tips with this are
to print out your dashboard before you get started
and label all the pieces and the number that you
want for the attributes. It's also a good idea
to set the ID attributes in increments of 10
because then when you go back and add something
else to the dashboard it's easier to add
a ID element for that new at that new piece
that you added in between two numbers that
have a range of 10 rather than having to
renumber all of your IDs to fit that piece in.
It's also helpful you can before you edit it in
the text editor you can set names for different
parts of your dashboard and that will make
it easier to figure out what should get what ID.
So this is an example of what it looks like
in the XML, and you'll notice I have some names
here, and I have my ID elements identified and
renumbered. And you can see the different zone
attributes that you get when you edit that XML
file. So once our focus order is set correctly
we can go through, and we've got the title then
we've got the date we've got our filters, most
recent day, past 10 days, and so on. And everything's
happening in a logical order, in the correct order,
and now when a user accesses this and is accessing
it by tabbing they're going to get the right order
and the top to bottom, left to right design
that we want as they access the dashboard.
Some other considerations for designing accessible
data visualizations. It's important to include
descriptive titles, subtitles, and captions, and this
is also important from a data literacy standpoint
and making sure that our dashboards and data
visualizations are understandable and clear
to all users. Also thinking about using tools
that have good screen reader compatibility
and good compatibility with other accessibility
web accessibility tools. Making sure we use alt
text to describe images and logos and
static pieces of a data visualization. Encoding
data with sound as well as visuals. And making
sure following the W3C accessibility guidelines
for the web which makes sure that the web and all
the parts of the web are accessible for all users.
And here I've just quoted the focus order
guideline 2.4.3 which makes sure that the web
can be navigated sequentially by all users. I hope
you found this talk useful. If you'd like to get
in touch with me, my website and twitter handle are
here. I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.